You know, your body is interlin. Your
heart, your lungs, your kidneys, they
all have to work together to keep you
the bright ray of sunshine that you are.
But that goes several steps further than
we realize. Like your brain, which
almost seems independent in its high
ivory tower, high above the rest of your
organs, barking commands to the rest of
the proletariat. Because it turns out
that the vessels feeding your brain may
in fact be revolting, increasing your
risk of cognitive decline. What am I odd
about? I'm talking about the plaque that
builds up in your arteries if you don't
take care of yourself over time,
secretreting messages that hijack your
brain's immune system, causing damage to
your brain. These things under a
microscope or in a bit of a cartoonish
style are called exosomes. They're these
vesicles, these little packages that
contain different molecules within them
that influence our cells. And it's been
recently discovered that when we build
up plaque in our arteries, our arterial
plaque begins releasing more of these
exosomes, which then travel throughout
the body, but importantly to the ivory
tower, our head, our brain. Once there,
they cause white matter lesions. What is
that, you might ask? Well, your brain is
split into two different compartments,
or at least it can be. You may have
heard of gray matter and white matter,
unrelated to dark matter, those
physicists go on about. Gray matter is
the actual body of the cell. You know
what? Let me throw a visual up for you.
The gray matter is the made up of the uh
different cell bodies. The white matter
on the other hand is the long
projections like tentacles that extend
away from the body called axons. These
axons are how we deliver information the
cell body to other regions of the brain
and often to another brain cell, another
neuron. These axons have a fatty sheath
like the sheath to a sword or when you
get rolled up in a blanket like a
tortilla. The axon is the tentacle from
the body. But the sheath called myelin
is the protector, the insulator. It
allows the messages, the electrical
signaling from the cell body to the end
of the axon at a much faster rate. That
sheath, the myelin, is what gives those
compartments of the brain the definition
of white matter. Now, I'm telling you
all that because the interconnectiveness
of your brain, the more intact
functioning white matter, the better
your brain health, all else equal. So we
understand what white matter is and we
understand that intact white matter is
important for cognitive health and this
is where white matter lesions can play a
disruptive role because it's an area of
damage within the white matter. Those
neat myelin sheets and potentially the
axons the communication tentacles are
damaged which impairs brain function.
That means in simple terms returning to
our exoomes, these messages released by
the plaque in our arteries are damaging
our brain. Okay, pretty fascinating in
its own right. But how is the brain
actually damaged by these messages? If I
chuck a letter at you, it's unlikely to
do much to you unless you get a paper
cut. And even then, you'll probably just
be a little bit annoyed. Same for the
brain. Well, when we take exoomes from
two groups of people, one group without
clinical atherosclerosis, so plaque and
arteries, and the other does have
atherosclerosis, and we apply these
exosomes to brain immune cells called
microglea, we get a set of revealing
reactions. Essentially when micro ga
those are the brain immune cells are
exposed to the exosomes produced by
people who have atherosclerosis they
increase the gene expression the
production of pro-inflammation
molecules. That's one thing but another
thing that they do is reduce the
activity of mitochondria. This all
points to microga. So these brain immune
cells being the prime suspect for these
exoomes to work through to cause this
brain damage. Think of it like the
exoomes are the messengers to the hitman
and the micro ga are the hitmen that
betray the mafia family. Isn't that
right?
But but there's still something
troubling me here because sure we have
the message. We sure we have the hitman,
but who would step out against the
family? Who instigated this atrocity?
We know it originates from the plaque
had built up in our arteries, but it's
not like exoomes package themselves and
spontaneously disappear. So, who's the
head dawn of this rival family? for
that. When we, and I mean scientists,
take samples from the human folk, we can
parse out the origin of this madness.
And this madness doesn't have to end
because this massive study that we're
going over has over a hundred pieces of
data describing all kinds of fascinating
aspects like what these exoomes are
carrying or what's the message itself,
the implications on our immune
mitochondria, the impact on our brain
performance, and more. If you're
interested in the full analysis, an
accompanying article, much extended
video, private podcast, and more, all
add free, plus live sessions with me,
yours truly. All that is exclusive to my
private community and research platform,
the Physiotic Insiders. Join me in the
community. Would love to have you
aboard. The link to join along with all
the perks explained is in the
description box. Hopefully, I'll see you
there. So, where is this all coming
from? our immune system, but not our
whole immune immune system. Only a
select very specific cell type in our
immune system. You may have heard of
this one before, but when we develop our
plaque in our arteries, certain immune
cells called macrofasages build up in
our plaque. They try to eliminate the
buildup of cholesterol and deposits in
the blood vessel, the artery wall. If
these macrofasages consume too much of
the cholesterol, they become
overburdened and turn into something
called a foam cell. These foam cells
secrete a lot of pro-inflammatory
molecules to attract more immune cells
to help them clear out the cholesterol
deposits. However, they also create
exoomes.
So this means that the dawn of the other
family creating the hit orders aka the
exoomes was trapped macrofasages inside
the plaque that had turned into bloated
foam cells. Now, all this research that
we've been over, and there's plenty more
in this study, mixing mechanistic mouse
data with with a breadth of human data,
all confirming this idea that plaque in
our arteries is not just a
cardiovascular disease risk, but
actively damages our brain, too. Even if
that plaque is not around our brain,
that said, I've covered many examples of
how to reduce our plaque burden and even
keep it at bay, which I'll link for you.
But the bottom line is this. We have
strong evidence that arterial plaque
harms our brain through immune cells
stuck in that arterial plaque that then
release messages in exosomes, little
vesicles, packages that then bind to
brain immune cells called micro ga
causing them to be aggressive and
destructive causing damage to our brain.
So this is all the more reason to keep
your arteries clear and healthy. And you
can do exactly that described across
many of my videos like this one or the
others that I'll link in the
description.
Someday that day may never come. I'll
call upon you to do service for me.
Actually, that call for service is right
now. It's furthering your health by
clicking on this next video. Thanks for
tuning in and let me know if you got the
reference. I'll see you in the next
ones.